Guide to the Mandy Carter Papers, 1970-2013 RL.00195
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mandy Carter papers
1970-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carter, Mandy
RL.00195
166.5 Linear Feet
Mandy Carter is a self-described "southern out black lesbian social justice activist." Since 1968 she has been involved in peace, social, racial and LGBT organizing at the local, state, regional, and national levels. She has been based in Durham, N.C., since 1982. The Mandy Carter Papers span the dates 1970 to 2013 and include files related to her work as a grassroots organizer and multi-issue social justice activist.
124875 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mandy Carter Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007, 2012 and 2013.
Biographical Note
Mandy Carter is a self-described "southern out black lesbian social justice activist." Since 1968, she has been involved in peace, social, racial and LGBT organizing at the local, state, regional, and national levels. She has been based in Durham, N.C., since 1982.
Chronology
1948 Nov. 2 Born, Albany, N.Y.
1948-1955 Albany Children's Home, Albany, N.Y.
1956-1959 Foster care, Chatham Center, N.Y.
1960-1966 Schenectady Children's Home, Schenectady, N.Y.
1966 Graduated, Mt. Pleasant High School, Schenectady, N.Y.
1966-1967 Attended Hudson Valley Community College, Troy, N.Y.
1967 Moved to New York City
1967 Volunteered at Timothy Leary's League for Spiritual Discovery
1968 Attended the Institute for the Study of Nonviolence, Carmel Valley, Calif.
1968 Participated in the Southern Christian Leadership Conference's Poor People's Campaign
1969-1973 Staff, War Resisters League, Western Regional Office, San Francisco, Calif.
1974-1977 Director, War Resisters League, Los Angeles, Calif.
1978 Founder/Coordinator, Women's Military Counter-Recruiting Campaign, San Francisco, Calif.
1979-1982 Bartender, Maud's; Co-manager, Amelia's; Coordinator, Women's Outreach, Gay and Lesbian Gay Olympics I; San Francisco, Calif.
1982-1988 Staff, War Resisters League, Southeast Regional Office, Durham, N.C.
1986-1990 Founding Co-producer, Real Women Productions, Durham, N.C.
1989 Wholesale distributor sales, Ladyslipper Inc., Durham, N.C.
1990 Campaign Manager, North Carolina Senate Vote '90, Durham, N.C.
1990-1994 Founding Co-producer and Box Office Coordinator, Rhythm Fest
1992-1995 Staff, Human Rights Campaign and Founder/Coordinator, A National Call to Resist: Countering the Radical Right in Our Black Community, Washington, D.C.
1993 Co-founder, Southerners on New Ground
1995-1996 Founder/Campaign Manager, North Carolina Mobilization '96, Durham, N.C.
1996-2000 Member-at-Large, Democratic National Committee; served on the Black Caucus and the Gay and Lesbian Caucus
1997-1998 National Field Director, National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum, Durham, N.C.
1998 Field Program Consultant, National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum, Washington, D.C.
2000 Campaign Manager, Floridians Representing Equity and Equality, Tampa, Fla.
2000 Campaign Manager, Florida Vote/Equal Voice, Miami, Fla.
2001-2002 Consultant, Freedom to Marry Project, Boston, Mass.
2003 Founding board member, National Black Justice Coalition
2003-2005 Executive Director, Southerners on New Ground, Durham, N.C.
2005 Nomination, 1000 Women for the Nobel Peace Prize
2008 National Co-chair, Obama LGBT Pride, Durham, N.C.
2012 Inducted into International Federation of Black Prides/Center for Black Equity
2013 Bayard Rustin Commemoration Project National Coordinator, Washington, D.C.
Collection Overview
The Mandy Carter Papers span the dates 1970 to 2013 and include files related to her work as a grassroots organizer and multi-issue social justice activist, with particular emphasis on peace activism, women's music and culture, and African American and LGBT issues.
The collection is arranged into the following series: Organizations and Major Projects, Gigs and Events, Administrative Files, and Subject Files. The Organizations and Projects Series (130 boxes) includes files from organizations and projects with which Carter was closely involved. The series is divided into subseries according to organization or project: Bread & Roses, War Resisters League, Ladyslipper, Inc., National Lesbian Conference, Association of Women's Music and Culture Conference, North Carolina Senate Vote '90, Real Women Productions, Rhythm Fest, Human Rights Campaign, North Carolina Mobilization '96, Democratic National Committee, National Black Lesbian & Gay Leadership Forum (including Equal Partners in Faith), Ad Hoc Committee for an Open Process, Floridians Representing Equity and Equality, Florida Vote/Equal Voice, Freedom to Marry Project, Southerners on New Ground, Old Lesbians Organizing for Change Conference, National Black Justice Coalition, and Other Organizations and Projects. The Gigs and Events Series (107 boxes) includes a day-by-day account of Carter's work as a multi-issue activist through files documenting her speaking engagements and attendance at conferences, rallies, marches, retreats, meetings, and other types of gatherings. The bulk of the Administrative Files Series (23 boxes) includes communications and mixed materials from affinity groups, and the Subject Files Series (4 boxes) includes a small set of files related to issues relevant to Carter's activism.
There is significant overlap across series, with Carter often filing materials related to different organizations or projects together, especially those she was involved with around the same time.
Collection was acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Related Material
Ladyslipper, Inc. Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Southerners on New Ground Records
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
War Resisters League, Southeast Regional Office Records
Southern Historical Collection, UNC Libraries
Oral histories with Mandy Carter
Southern Oral History Program, UNC Libraries
Gay rights -- United States; Lesbian activists -- United States; Lesbian community -- North Carolina; Lesbians -- North Carolina -- Durham; Pacifists -- United States; Peace movements -- United States; Same-sex marriage -- United States; Social change -- North Carolina; Washington (D.C.); North Carolina; Durham (N.C.); Women's music festivals; African American lesbians -- United States; Community activists -- North Carolina -- Durham; Gay pride celebrations; Women's music; Ad Hoc Committee for an Open Process; Southerners on New Ground; War Resisters League -- Southeast; Real Women Productions; Rhythm Fest; Human Rights Campaign (U.S); National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum (U.S.); National Black Justice Coalition; North Carolina Mobilization; National Lesbian Conference (1991: Atlanta, Ga.); Old Lesbians Organizing for Change; Bread & Roses (Organization); North Carolina Senate Vote; Ladyslipper, Inc.; Association of Women's Music and Culture Conference (1991: Durham, N.C.); Carter, Mandy; Carter, Mandy; Florida Vote/Equal Voice; Democratic National Committee (U.S.); Freedom to Marry Project; Floridians Representing Equity and Equality
- Organizations and Projects Series, 1972-2006, 130 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes files from organizations and projects with which Carter was closely involved. The series is divided into subseries according to organization or project. Subseries descriptions include a broad overview of each organization or project, as well as a summary of Carter's involvement.
  The series is presented in rough chronological order. Original order has been maintained to the extent possible, though dispersed materials related to a particular organization were brought together during processing. For the most part, original file folder titles were retained, though some files were combined or renamed for clarification purposes and unfoldered materials were integrated during processing.
  Due to the overlapping nature of her work, Carter often filed materials related to different organizations or projects together, especially those she was involved with around the same time. As a result, materials related to organizations and projects below may also be found in the Gigs and Events Series and the Administrative Files Series.
  - Bread & Roses Subseries, 1979-1982, 1 box
    Bread & Roses is a non-profit organization based in California that brings free, live entertainment to people who live in institutions. From 1979 to 1982, Carter served as the front of house volunteer coordinator for the annual Festival of Music.
    Includes materials related to the logistics of organizing volunteer ushers, such as volunteer lists, schedules, assignments, meeting notes, and maps, as well as some promotional materials.
    - Bread & Roses files (Box 59)
  - War Resisters League Subseries, 1972-2002, 5 boxes
    The War Resisters League (WRL) is a pacifist organization founded in 1923. Carter was on staff at the Western Regional Office in San Francisco, California, from October 1969 to December 1973, and served as Director of the Los Angeles office from January 1974 to December 1977. She joined the staff of the Southeast Regional Office in Durham, North Carolina, in November 1982 and worked there until December 1988.
    The bulk of the material dates from Carter's time with the Southeast Regional Office (1982-1988). Local and regional actions for peace, especially in the Middle East, as well as a number of demonstrations against nuclear proliferation are documented through correspondence, meeting notes, administrative files, pamphlets, flyers and clippings. The series also includes files from WRL national and regional offices, retreats, executive and national committee meetings, as well as newsletters and reports from related organizations.
    Files from the 1970s include a packet of readings on feminism and non-violence from the San Francisco office and financials from the Los Angeles office. Materials from the 1990s and 2000s include mailings to supporters and files on anniversary events in which Carter participated.
    - WRL files (Box 42-43, 109-111, 280)
  - Ladyslipper, Inc. Subseries, 1988-1999, 1 box
    In 1989, Carter worked in wholesale distributor sales at Ladyslipper, Inc., ta distributor of women's music, with offices in Durham, North Carolina. Carter also served as a board member.
    Includes files related to events, fundraising efforts, and a concert by Joan Baez one by Cris Williamson and Teresa Trull, as well as press releases, budgets, meeting notes, some correspondence, job descriptions, personnel policies, and a handful of catalogs from the 1990s. Board meeting minutes can be found in the Gigs and Events Series.
    - Ladyslipper Music files (Box 54)
  - National Lesbian Conference Subseries, 1988-1990, 3 boxes
    The National Lesbian Conference was held April 24-28, 1991, in Atlanta, Georgia, though meetings to plan and organize the conference were held across the United States beginning in 1988. Carter helped organize the first national planning meeting held March 3-6, 1989, in Durham, North Carolina, and continued to participate in the planning process as part of the Mobilization Committee of the Interim Task Committee.
    Materials document planning meetings held at the national, Southern regional, and North Carolina statewide levels as well as interim steering committee meetings in Atlanta. Includes meeting notes by Carter, as well as meeting schedules, agendas and minutes; personal and organizational letters, including updates; committee lists; and publicity, such as press releases and flyers. Pamphlets, newsletters, and other materials from LGBT organizations are interfiled.
    - National Lesbian Conference files (Box 47, 62-63)
  - Association of Women's Music and Culture Conference Subseries, 1988-1991, 3 boxes
    The Association of Women's Music and Culture (AWMAC) was an international professional organization that aimed to further the development of women's music and culture by providing services for musicians and those who created opportunities for music to reach audiences. In 1991, the AWMAC Conference was held in Durham, North Carolina, coinciding with the 15th anniversary of Ladyslipper, Inc. Carter served as Conference Coordinator and was responsible for forming a host committee to handle local logistics.
    The bulk of the materials relate to preparations for the 1991 annual conference, including meeting and planning notes, flyers and promotional materials, schedules, registration materials, programs, and correspondence, as well as materials related to event venues and hotels. Also includes programs and other materials from previous conferences.
    - AWMAC files (Box 44-46)
  - North Carolina Senate Vote '90 Subseries, 1990, 17 boxes
    North Carolina Senate Vote '90 (NCSV '90) was a political action committee that undertook a statewide, county-by-county lesbian, gay, and bisexual voter registration campaign in an effort to unseat Republican Senator Jesse Helms and elect Harvey Gantt, who had served as the first black mayor of Charlotte, North Carolina, from 1983 to 1987. Carter served as Campaign Manager, working on behalf of NCSV '90 for most of 1990. Carter formed a similar organization, North Carolina Mobilization '96, when Gantt challenged Helms for his Senate seat again in 1996.
    Includes meeting minutes and meeting notes; planning documents, such as schedules and timelines; correspondence; office reports and updates; files related to planning events, such as fundraising benefits, rallies, and major meetings; voter registration information for counties across North Carolina and get-out-the-vote kits; materials related to fundraising and financials, including budgets, funding plans, records of pledges and donations, quarterly reports, and filings with the Federal Election Commission; designs and order forms for anti-Helms merchandise; donor lists, contact lists and mailing lists; publicity materials, including mailings, press releases, flyers for events and meetings, print ads, radio ad scripts and radio station research; files related to volunteer recruitment and organization, including sign-up forms, time logs, and schedules; and research files on both Helms and Gantt, which include media clippings, political cartoons, fundraising letters and campaign materials, voting records, and position papers.
    - NCSV '90 files (Box 36-40, 69-74, 223-227, 265)
  - Real Women Productions Subseries, 1986-1990, 4 boxes
    Real Women Productions existed from about 1986 to 1990. Loosely organized, it began when Mandy Carter, Lucy Harris, Cheri Sistek, and Cris South began working to bring women's entertainment and culture to Durham, North Carolina, and the surrounding areas. The group produced different types of shows, including music, comedy, and dance. Many shows were presented in conjunction with other organizations, such as Triangle Area Lesbian Feminists, the War Resisters League, and North Carolina Senate Vote '90, and often served as a fundraising mechanism with proceeds benefitting non-profit organizations in the area.
    Includes materials related to the production of shows, including contracts, riders, promotional materials, correspondence, budgets and expenses, space and equipment rental agreements, and schedules, as well as correspondence regarding bookings and performances, meeting notes, related news clippings, and artist information packets and promo materials.
    - Real Women Productions files (Box 105-108)
  - Rhythm Fest Subseries, 1990-1995, 6 boxes
    Rhythm Fest was a women's music, arts, and politics festival held Labor Day weekend in the South beginning in 1990. Carter was a founding co-producer of the event and served as box office coordinator from 1990 to 1994.
    Materials relate to the logistics of planning the festival and include correspondence; notes from meetings and calls; receipt books; files regarding ticketing and work exchanges; promotional materials, such as flyers, pamphlets, mailings, and clippings of paid advertisements; and evaluation forms. The series also includes a small number of materials from other women's festivals.
    - Rhythm Fest files (Box 41, 87-90, 265, 280)
  - Human Rights Campaign Subseries,1990-2001, 23 boxes
    Founded in 1980, the Human Rights Campaign (HRC) is a national organization that advocates for LGBT equality through lobbying and grassroots organizing. Carter worked for the HRC from April 1992 through November 1995. During this time, she was the Southeast Field Coordinator, the Northern California Coordinator for the HRC Campaign '92, Public Policy Advocate for 10 Southern States Congressional Delegations, and Founder/Coordinator of A National Call to Resist: Countering the Radical Right in Our Black Community, a joint project with the National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum. She was also involved in a number of campaigns against specific anti-gay ballot measures, such as Vote No On 1 in Tampa, Fla.
    Materials reflect involvement in the projects listed above and include meeting notes; training materials from workshops; conference materials and packets; mailing lists; communications, including mail, memos, email, and faxes; internal reports, including monthly reports from the Public Policy Department and reports from Board of Directors meetings; informational materials distributed by HRC, such as newsletters, mailings, press releases, action alerts, pamphlets, one-sheets, and house party packets; subject files, including materials on gay men and lesbians in the military, the Employment Non-Discrimination Act, anti-gay sentiment and actions, and the religious right; clippings; and research files on legislative activities and Members of Congress, including legislative reports and voting records.
    - HRC files (Box 10-24, 228-234, 265, 280)
  - North Carolina Mobilization '96 Subseries, 1990-1997, 11 boxes
    North Carolina Mobilization '96 (NC Mobe) was a political action committee that led a grassroots effort to mobilize North Carolina's lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and ally voters, volunteers, and money to defeat Senator Jesse Helms and elect Harvey Gantt. This was the second time Gantt challenged Helms for his seat in the United States Senate. The first time was in 1990, and Carter had led a similar organization, North Carolina Senate Vote '90, to unseat Helms and support Gantt. Carter founded the organization and served as campaign manager, working with NC Mobe for much of 1996.
    Includes meeting materials and notes; planning documents, such as calendars and work plans; communications, including correspondence, email and phone messages; office reports and updates; materials related to financials and fundraising, including filings with the Federal Election Commission; files related to volunteer recruitment, orientation, and training; publicity materials, including mailings, press releases, print ads and inserts, and flyers for events and meeting; pages printed from the NC Mobe website; get-out-the-vote kits; research files on North Carolina, including voter guidelines; orders for anti-Helms merchandise; donor lists, contact lists and mailing lists; clippings; research files on both Helms and Gantt; and materials from other anti-Helms groups.
    - NC Mobe '96 files (Box 1-9, 235-236, 280)
  - Democratic National Committee Subseries, 1992-2001, 3 boxes
    From May to June 1996, Carter was a consultant to the Office of Lesbian and Gay Outreach of the Democratic National Committee (DNC). In this role, she worked with existing gay and lesbian democratic clubs around the country to organize voter registration drives in their own communities. From 1996 to 2000, Carter served as a North Carolina Member-At-Large of the DNC. During this time she was involved with the Gay and Lesbian Caucus and the Black Caucus. She was also a delegate for Al Gore at the Democratic National Convention in 2000.
    Includes memos and other communications, meeting agendas and notes, and briefings and reports from both caucuses, as well as files from DNC meetings and communications regarding the Gore presidential campaign. Also includes files related to the 2000 Democratic National Convention.
    - DNC files (Box 29, 33, 91)
  - National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum Subseries, 1992-1999, 6 boxes
    Founded in 1988, the National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum (NBLGLF) worked to empower black lesbians, gay men, bisexuals, and transgender people by developing their leadership skills, increasing visibility, and bringing communities together. The organization disbanded in 2003. While on staff at the HRC, Carter worked in conjunction with the NBLGLF on joint projects, such as the People of Color Summit and A National Call to Resist: Countering the Radical Right in Our Black Community. Carter also worked as National Field Director of the NBLGLF from March 1997 to March 1998 and as Field Program Consultant from August 1998 to December 1998.
    Includes research files, primarily clippings, on the radical right; articles about or written by Carter; work plans and budgets for the National Field Program, including work plans for specific cities (Denver, Washington, D.C., Charlotte); communications, including emails, faxes, and letters; mailings and materials for the Board of Directors; speeches; meeting notes; contracts and files related to fundraising, budgets, and donors; and records related to the annual conference.
    Materials related to joint projects by the HRC and NBLGLF can be found in both subseries. People of Color Summit materials in this subseries include registration forms, materials for summit packets, clippings, press releases, and meeting notes.
    - NBLGLF files (Box 48-53)
  - Equal Partners in Faith Subseries, 1996-1998, 6 boxes
    Equal Partners in Faith was a multiracial grassroots coalition of people of faith committed to equality and diversity. The coalition coordinated a response to "Stand in the Gap: A Sacred Assembly of Men," a rally held on October 4, 1997, in Washington, D.C., by the Promise Keepers, an evangelical Christian men's-only movement associated with the religious right. In the fall of 1997, Carter was on special assignment from the NBLGLF, serving as Program Director for Equal Partners in Faith.
    Includes research files on Promise Keepers, primarily clippings and printed website pages; meeting notes; communications, including memos, emails, faxes, and phone messages; media plans; files related to events; contact lists; and funding proposals.
    - Equal Partners in Faith files (Box 30, 64-65, 92-94)
  - Ad Hoc Committee for an Open Process Subseries, 1998-2000, 1.5 boxes
    Carter was a member of the Ad Hoc Committee for an Open Process, which formed in response to what members saw as a poorly conceived and non-inclusive planning process for the Millennium March on Washington, an event organized by the HRC and Metropolitan Community Churches to raise awareness and visibility of LGBT people and issues. It was held April 28-April 30, 2000 in Washington, D.C.. Previously, Carter served on the National Steering Committee for the March on Washington in 1987 and 1993.